hello and welcome back to real analysis and
as always i want to thank all the nice people
that support this channel on steady or paypal
in today's part 16 we will still talk about
series and we have already learned a series is
just a special sequence namely it's simply the
sequence of partial sums for a given sequence
a k hence the sum ends here with a new index n
now because you already know this definition you
see we don't have a problem when we start a sum
with another number which is not 1. so depending
on the sequence ak we can start here with 0 2 or
3 or even a negative number if it makes sense
i tell you that because in the next example we
have a series that starts with zero it's the very
important geometric series and there we sum all
the powers of a given number q hence for us first
q could be any real number however what we want
to show now is that this series is convergent if
and only if q is less than 1 in the absolute value
hence only in this case we get a finite
number when calculating this infinite sum
okay then let's start the calculation the overall
question is of course what is our sequence sn
the sequence of partial sums because when we know
this we can calculate the limit n to infinity
indeed there is a nice calculation we can do with
this sum in the case that q is not equal to 1.
of course this is not a restriction because if
q is equal to 1 we have a very simple sum here
we just sum up once and therefore the series is
divergent to infinity okay now in the case that
q is not 1 we can multiply the whole sum with
1 minus q so we just scale the sequence here
with a non-zero number now the overall idea
is that we can expand this expression here
and get two sums the first sum is the same as
before and the second has q to the power k plus 1.
and now what we can do is change the
index here such that we have again
q to the power k inside the sum this simply
means that we start with k is equal to 1
and go to n plus one and then you should
see we go exactly through the same numbers
okay such an index shift is very helpful because
now we can subtract the two sums here and the only
things that remain are for the first sum the first
index so k is equal to 0 and for the second sum
the last index so k is equal to n plus 1. hence
we have q to the power 0 which is by definition
1 and q to the power n plus one okay with this we
have a very nice expression for our sequence sn
namely we can just divide by one minus q which
is non-zero and get this nice formula here and
there you should immediately see in which cases
sn is a convergent sequence we just have to know
if the sequence q to the power n is convergent
this is what you might already know and it is not
hard to show q to the power n is convergent if and
only if the absolute value of q is less than one
and in this case we also know the limit
which is zero then this implies that we can
actually calculate the limit of this sequence
here and as you can see this is 1 over 1 minus q
hence in summary the value of our series here
is well defined for q in the absolute value less
than 1 and it is 1 over 1 minus q this is such an
important formula such that it gets its own name
it's called the geometric series and you
really should remember it of course you can
see that this formula is important because
it got a name therefore i can now tell you
there is another series that has a special name
this one is the so-called harmonic series and
indeed it's an example of a divergent series it's
constructed by summing up all fractions one over k
so we have one plus one half plus one third plus
one fourth and so on and now we will show that
this is not convergent but rather divergent
to plus infinity the first time you see this
it might be a little bit surprising because
each number we add gets smaller and smaller
however the whole sum increases as much as you
want and this is exactly what we now want to show
therefore let's look again at the partial sums
we call sn here you should see immediately that
this is a sequence of positive real numbers
that is also monotonically increasing hence
the only thing that remains to show is that the
sequence is not bounded in order to show this we
have different possibilities but i choose a very
simple one we will only look at the indices where
n is a power of 2. there you will see this makes
everything easier in the first step you should
see we can rewrite this number as differences this
means that i can start with s1 and then i go to s2
but then i subtract s1 again hence this whole term
is just s2 then we go to s4 and subtract s2 again
in other words this is just s4 and please recall i
just want to use the powers of 2 here therefore in
the next step i would use s8 and subtract s4 again
and then we continue the whole game until we reach
our index 2 to the power m and of course in this
last step we have to subtract the predecessor in
summary this is just a complicated way to write s
with index 2 to the power m however still this is
very helpful because now we have differences here
and these differences are much easier to estimate
of course if you don't like the dots here we
can simply put the whole formula into a sum
symbol here it has the same information but now
it's compact but we have to use another index j
okay at this point you should recall that s
with an index stands for partial sum so here
we subtract two partial sums and of course what
remains is the middle part of the partial sum
okay so let's write that into another line okay so
we know we get out a partial sum the only thing we
have to think about is what is the start index and
what is the end index for this we call that this
partial sum once to the end index 2 to the
power j and this end index is smaller than this
hence the final index has to be 2 to the power
j also we know all indices that are smaller than
this or equal will vanish hence the start index
has to be 2 to the power j minus 1 plus 1. of
course this looks complicated because of all
the indices involved but actually it's not so
complicated because it's just a small part of this
sum here therefore maybe for the visualization
just imagine that the sum stands for these three
numbers here then of course the sum gets smaller
when we don't add one half plus one third plus
one fourth but rather three times one quarter here
indeed that is what we can do in general when we
put in here for the fraction the largest index
now we just have to count how many
times we add this constant number here
and when you do this you see we have
exactly 2 to the power j minus 1 terms
hence this is the only product we have to
calculate now and because we have chosen the
powers of two this is not so complicated it
is exactly one half now this is an important
information because it tells us that this term
here is always greater than one half no matter
what j is so we have this factor one half m
times in conclusion here we have our estimate
the partial sum s with index two to the power m
is always greater than s one plus m times one half
and of course this is not bounded at all because
when m increases this goes to infinity hence we
have shown that the whole sequence of partial sums
is not bounded from above in combination with the
monotonicity we have our divergence to infinity
hence there we have our harmonic series which is
a divergent series so please remember also this
important result okay then in the next videos we
will talk more about criteria we can use to show
the convergence of series and you will also see
that the two examples we had here are also very
helpful there so i hope i see you next time bye
you